<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Phenotypic</title><link href="http://phenotypic.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://phenotypic.net/feeds/Articles.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://phenotypic.net/</id><updated>2013-10-07T21:53:38-07:00</updated><entry><title>The Race for New Heart Drugs</title><link href="http://phenotypic.net/the-race-for-new-heart-drugs.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-07T21:53:38-07:00</updated><author><name></name></author><id>tag:phenotypic.net,2013-10-07:the-race-for-new-heart-drugs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With all the hype over personalized medicine the past few years, the field has yet to deliver on translating the Human Genome Project into clinical value beyond the mountains of sequencing data. But, in a unique approach combining detailed subject physiological information and genomic data, hope and hype surrounds a new low-density lipoprotein (LDL) target to battle heart disease.  The underlying truth of the gene PCSK9  is currently being revealed in clinical studies to develop new cholesterol fighting, antibodies. It’s also making pharma CEOs salivate with direct to consumer ads buzzing in their eardrums. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this enzyme (full name: proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9) fascinating and potentially worth billions for drug developers? It’s ability to push LDL (aka “bad cholesterol”) to unseen low levels as reported in mid-stage clinical studies from Pfizer (New Jersey), Sanofi (France), and Amgen (America). These companies and a few others have touted positive results in toxicity and efficacy, with the pivotal &lt;a href="http://Clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=PCSK9+AND+low+density+lipoprotein+cholesterol"&gt;Phase III studies&lt;/a&gt; now in the limelight.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discovery of this enzyme as a potential blockbuster cholesterol therapy stems from the novel way in that the clinical studies were designed.  Based off early studies, it was inferred that a knockout mutation in PCSK9 would result in significantly lower cholesterol levels.  &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/genetics-a-gene-of-rare-effect-1.12773"&gt;Clinical research team Helen Hobbs and Jonathan Cohen&lt;/a&gt; at UT Southwestern took people with extremely high and low LDL, stratified them accordingly, and it eventually demonstrated the low LDL group had a missense mutation in their PCSK9 gene.  In a nutshell, they started with the phenotypic basis of heart disease and reduced down to Mendelian level genetics to illustrate mutation’s role in keeping cholesterol levels down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current treatment for high cholesterol predominantly consists of statins (e.g., Lipitor, Crestor).  According to rock star physician Eric Topol, &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/05/opinion/the-diabetes-dilemma-for-sta
tin-users.html?_r=0"&gt;statins only reduces the rate&lt;/a&gt; of heart attack’s in patients trying to lower the risk to a pathetic 2 in 100, and there are harmful side effects such as forgetfulness and muscle pain. So clearly there is need for better medications to treat heart disease.  Large-scale randomized controlled trial data will be the next step for the aforementioned drug companies to showcase if approval for the drug is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since these new classes of drugs are expensive monoclonal antibodies, they may need to be significantly more effective than current treatments to receive FDA approval.  Antibody therapeutics are notoriously pricey, and these could very well cost patients tens of thousands of dollars.  If one of the companies can formulate into a cheaper, oral pill then that may give them an advantage over competition. These are some of the important questions to consider if any of the drugs can fine their way to the marketplace. &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Summer Reading</title><link href="http://phenotypic.net/summer-reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-20T07:29:25-07:00</updated><author><name></name></author><id>tag:phenotypic.net,2013-06-20:summer-reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Man In the High Castle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by Philip k. Dick&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A romp through an alternate history years after WWII where the Germans won and an arms race is occurring between them and the Japanese. It's a tale of an alternative present, questioning our perception of reality and the records that follow.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Python Programming: An Introduction to Computer Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by John Zelle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is only not utterly borring when a finished product is involved (e.g., this blog), and I hope to generate more tangible goods soon.  Looking to do something "data analysis" related next time to pair with my science background.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ted Chiang's short story collection, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Story of Your Life and Others&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorites from the book was originally published in Nature as &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v405/n6786/full/405517a0.html"&gt;Catching Crumbs from the Table&lt;/a&gt;.  It is a futuristic look at a research world dominated by metahumans, causing a knowledge gap for human scientists. Not as dystopian as it sounds.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many articles and a few books on current trends in biotech and healthcare. On deck is a book touting     the benefits of personalized healthcare, titled &lt;a href="http://www.%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20amazon.com/The-Creative-Destruction-Medicine-Revolution/dp/0465025501"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Creative Destruction of Medicine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Search of Lost Time, vol 1: Swann's Way&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by Marcel Proust&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passages in this book will exercise your memory facilities, conjuring up thoughts, feelings, you have not revisited in many years.  2013 also marks the &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2013/05/02/books/proust-project.html?_r=0#/#weber1"&gt;100th anniversary&lt;/a&gt; of its publication.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Mapping the Brain with Big Science</title><link href="http://phenotypic.net/mapping-the-brain-with-big-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-31T20:52:37-07:00</updated><author><name></name></author><id>tag:phenotypic.net,2013-03-31:mapping-the-brain-with-big-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At a time when only &lt;a href="http://report.nih.gov/success_rates/"&gt;1 in 5&lt;/a&gt; researchers secure grant funding and many scientists are struggling to find qualified work, details recently emerged on a potential groundbreaking project called the Brain Activity Map (aka BAM).  The multi-billion dollar proposal follows in the footsteps of similar large-scale science projects such as the Human Genome and recent ENCODE.  Initial reports of BAM occurred after President Obama’s State of The Union address, where he once again emphasized the importance of Science &amp;amp; Technology  (STEM) to ease the nations fears. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project, which the administration has been looking to unveil as early as March, will include federal agencies, private foundations and teams of neuroscientists and nanoscientists in a concerted effort to advance the knowledge of the brain’s billions of neurons and gain greater insights into       perception, actions and, ultimately, consciousness.
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/18/science/project-seeks-to-build-map-of-human-brain.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=0"&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complex proposal involves studying all cell types of the brain, and dissecting each of their roles in neuronal pathways. Many of the current technologies studying the brain are limited in sensitivity. For example, &lt;a href="http://pleasandexcuses.com/2012/08/01/what-the-heck-does-a-brain-scan-really-measure/"&gt;fMRI relies of changes in blood flow patterns&lt;/a&gt; to estimate brain activity. Various technologies such as nanonsensors, 3D imaging, and synthetic biology would need to be developed and refined to measure brain signaling pathways for BAM to deliver cutting edge results.  The Obama administration wants scientists to come up with homerun answers for complex problems such as obesity and neurodegeneration.  But, considering we are still piecing together the interworking’s of lower animal brains (e.g, fruit flies, rodents), the ~ 3 lb. blob in our skulls seems incredibly daunting.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important concern surrounds the cost/benefit of these “Big Science” endeavors.   Molecular biologist, George Church, said in the NYTs that “we will probably get a lot more bang for the buck,” when compared to the Human Genome Project.  The benefits of the Genome Project really depend on whom you ask.  Many private genomic sequencing firms dominate biotech headlines with their venture capital funding, but the clinical benefits are just now bearing fruit.  Prenatal genetic screening is a recent example (23 years after that project's inception) and is still not a clinical standard.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word on the project’s funding fate is expected to occur anytime.  Regardless of the funding decision, more neuroscience research money is warranted to make needed progress on the brain disorders affecting so many people.  The current rates of Alzheimer's disease alone justifies a full-fledged public health crisis.  That said, the payoff from mapping these human neuronal pathways with BAM would be years down the road. While transhumanists may praise such a proposal, its promise is still in the realm of science fiction with little translatable to the clinic. But even more disturbing, this heavy, top-down approach only consolidates research funds to a select group of powerful scientists. As Michael Eison of UC-Berkeley recently said in &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/behind-the-scenes-of-a-brain-mapping-moon-shot-1.12543"&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;, “What motivates people to pursue these big projects is not the belief that they will solve problems… It’s the belief that this is the way to get money.”&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>